But it will be a while before we can test this in our code. We still are going
to implement a whole layer on top of it along with a bunch of UI changes.
Fortunately, we can implement J unit test here to help. And now for
some magic. We'll add a directory to the source directory of our Android studio
project called Android test. And then, another one underneath it called Java.
This is the way we tell Android studio there's a test target in cradle for
our app. Now we create a test package that matches our main package with
an extra test directory on the end. Create a new class called full
test suite in the test package. Add this code. This
is some boiler plate code that will allow us to add tests in additional classes.
Next, we'll create a TestDb class that extends Android test case [NOISE] and
add a test that creates our Db. The way this works is that the test runner
will execute every function in our class that begins with test in the order that
they are declared in the class. Each test should have a failure path that
uses an assert. We start by deleting the database before testing it. So,
we have a clean test. Now, to run the test we go to the app start drop down.
And select Edit Configurations. We select Plus to add a new configuration. And
select Android Tests Against Module App. Now we name the test.
Now note that it tends to target the emulator by default. So,
I want to use an actual device I'm going to select Show Chooser Dialogue.
Now we can just run the test against our device. And, it passes. So
let's create a data base insert and read test. At the beginning of it,
we'll insert a single record into each table. We'll begin with some dummy
data for our location. We'll use the dbHelper to get a writeable database.
This is exactly how we will use the database when we code it up in our project.
We'll then create a ContentValues object, which is a handy helper object that
Android uses to store values and keys. We'll store our dummy data into
the columns from our LocationEntry contract. Note that in order to make it
work with this abbreviated syntax, I did have to add some extra imports up here.
We then insert the data into our data base, and verified that we got a row back.
Now I find that it's helpful to put log messages into my test cases.
Now we'll use the database read operations to pull our dummy data back out of
the data base. We're making use of a custom projection here which, in theory,
would make it easy to use our database cursor to query for the values we want.
We use a custom projection here. Although, it's not required.
If the custom projection wasn't there, we would simply return all columns.
A database cursor is a control structure that enables traversal over
the records in a database. In Android, this is represented by a cursor object.
The cursor object allows one to traverse between records in a query and
get the contents of any individual column from a query.
Now, we use cursor.moveToFirst to populate our cursor with our row of data.
We can then pull out our data by index. Finally assert
if it doesn't match our dummy data. And now, we get to run our tests again.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And they passed.